Guide to the Marcel Montassut Papers, 1914-1975 RL.10169
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Marcel Montassut papers
1914-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
History of Medicine Collections (Duke University)
Montassut, Marcel
RL.10169
2 Linear Feet
Pyschiatrist of Villejuif and Moiselles, France. The collection (300 items; dated 1914-1975) contains the papers of Marcel Montassut, a noted French psychiatrist who worked in the Hôpital Psychiatrique de Villejuif as Médecin-Chef from 1942 to 1960. Montassut's papers are primarily research-oriented and include several of his publications, notes on particular subject areas, and reviews of work in the field of psychiatry. Also present are civil and military documents pertaining to Montassut, as well as correspondence between colleagues, including the noted French psychiatrist Léon Chertok. The bulk of his research is founded in studies on depression, melancholia, and epilepsy. Additionally, the papers include documents related to his professional involvement as interim director at the Centre Neuro-Psychiatrique de Moiselles and as president of the Société Française de Médecine Psychosomatique.
Historical note
Dr. Marcel Montassut, a French psychiatrist, was born on August 14, 1897. Professionally, Montassut worked in the Centre Neuro-Psychiatrique de Moiselles as an interim director in 1940, as well as at the Hôpital Psychiatrique de Villejuif as Médecin-Chef from 1942 to 1960. During World War I and World War II, he served as a medical assistant and doctor. Montassut also held the presidency of the Société Française de Médécine Psychosomatique in 1960. He married in 1937 and spent much of his career in Villejuif. During his lifetime, Montassut published many articles on depression, epilepsy, fatigue, and psychosomatics. He worked closely with Léon Chertok, a well-known French psychiatrist. Montassut died in 1975.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: Personal files, Writings, and Subject files. Arranged alphabetically.
Collection Overview
The collection documents the work of noted French psychiatrist Marcel Montassut, and includes his correspondence, writings, research notes, and official civil and military documents. Of particular note are Monstassut’s letters with noted French psychiatrist Léon Chertok and the revised transcript of his book, "La dépression constitutionelle." The bulk of his research materials pertain to depression, melancholia, and epilepsy. The collection also includes documents related to his professional involvement as interim director at the Centre Neuro-Psychiatrique de Moiselles and as president of the Société Française de Médecine Psychosomatique. Acquired as part of the History of Medicine Collections.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Certain documents with patient information have been restricted until 2034. Redacted photocopies can be found in respective folders. Restricted items are found in a folder at the end of the collection in Box 2.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Marcel Montassut Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in August 2014 as part of the History of Medicine Collections.
History of Medicine; Villejuif (France); Psychiatry; Certok, Léon; History of Medicine Collections (Duke University); Montassut, M. (Marcel); Montassut, Marcel; Société française de médecine psychosomatique
- Personal Files, 1914-1975
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes materials related to Montassut's involvement in professional organizations, as well as his identity documents, correspondence, and an obituary. Some files with patient information are restricted until 2034; however, redacted photocopies of this material have been made available.
  - Centre Neuro-Psychiatrique de Moisellesm, 1940 (Box 1)
    Correspondence, clippings, and files during Montassut's interim service as Médecin-Capitaine at the Centre Neuro-Psychiatrique de Moisselles.
  - Cirriculum Vitaes, 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Civil/medical identity documents, 1975 (Box 1)
    Syndicat de la Presse Scientifique; Fiche individuelle d'etat civil et de nationalité française
  - Compagnie Nationale Air France, 1961-1965 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1926-1974 (Box 1)
    General correspondence, including during Montassut's presidency of the Société Française de Médécine Psychosomatique, with the Préfecture de Police, and one letter with L. Chertok, a noted French psychiatrist.
  - Hôpital Psychiatrique de Villejuif, 1942-1960 (Box 1)
    From Montassut's work as Médecin-Chef at the Psychiatric Hospital in Villejuif. Includes a list of assistant attachés and interns, correspondence, files on the projet du service libre, and annual reports.
  - Military identity documents, 1917-1961 (Box 1)
    Includes carte d'identité de sanitaire, travel documents, and summaries of service.
  - Obituary, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Premier Congres de Médécine Psychosomatique, 1960 (Box 1)
    Includes address given by Montassut at the conference.
  - Société Française de Médécine Psychosomatique, 1960 (Box 1)
    From the time Montassut served as President. Includes letterhead, statutes, founder lists, and member lists.
  - Postal Work, 1914 (Box 1)
    From Montassut's first job in Postal Administration.
- Writings
  This series contains writings and lectures by Marcel Montassut, including a a revised transcript of his book "La dépression constitutionelle." Also includes two binders that housed Montassut's personal collection of his publications in chronological order. A title list is provided for each binder.
  - Binder 1, 1922-1926 (Box 1)
    “Délire systématisé fantastique à base d’imagination et d’hallucinations,” 1922 “Délire d’imagination,” 1923 “Tics respiratoires et troubles mentaux au cours d’une encéphalite épidémique fruste,” 1923 “Désagrégation de la personnalité au cours d’un délire d’influence chez une dégénérée,” 1924 “Un cas de ‘syndrome des sosies’ chez une délirante hallucinée par interprétation des troubles psycho-sensoriels,” 1925 “Le traitement des états anxieux par le gardénal à doses réfractées,” 1925 “La constitution paranoïaque,” 1925 «Un délire de compensation,” 1924 “L’hyperpnée dans la diagnostic de l’épilepsie psychique,” 1925 “Note sur les modifications sanguines au cours de l’hyperpnée volontaire,” 1925 “La compensation idéo-affective,” 1925 “Épreuve de l’hyperpnée dans les psychoses,” 1925 “Psychose intermittente atypique simulant la démence précoce,” 1925 “Léon Bloy, Pélerin de l’absolu,” 1926 “Délimitation de la paranoïa légitime,” 1926 “Présidence de M. Henri Claude,” 1926 “Sur le rôle de l’alcalose dans l’épilepsie convulsive,” 1926 “Les troubles de la cénesthésie,” 1926 “Cénesthopathie et périodicité,” 1926
  - Binder 2, 1927-1930 (Box 1)
    “Hépatisme et fatigue,” 1927 “Action des chocs sur des chiens porteurs de lésions rolandiques,” 1927 “Action préventive du choc anaphylactique sur les convulsions des chiens ‘épileptisés’ à la strychnine,” 1927 “Épilepsie et choc anaphylactique,” 1927 “Interprétation délirante d’actes automatiques comitiaux,” 1927 “Rythme paradoxal de la sensation de fatigue et de l’asthénie dans une forme particulière de neurasthénie,” 1928 “Rythmes quotidiens de fatigue au cours des asthénies,” 1928 “Amélioration d’une psychose hallucinatoire sous l’influence du traitement pyrétique et anti-infectieux,” 1929 “Neurasthénies syphilitiques,” 1929 “Neurasthénie et oxalémie,” 1930 “Etude Clinique et nosologique de la dépression psycho-musculaire chronique avec émotivité constitutionnelle,” 1930 “Emotivité, potassium et calcium plasmatiques,” 1930 “Sédation d’une exoitation maniaque par ingestion de Cacl,” 1930 “Epilepsie et accidents hypoglycémiques chez un Parkinsonien traité à l’insuline,” 1930 “Le magnésium chez les déprimés émotifs,” 1930 “La fatigue du neurasthénique,” 1930 [unpublished]
  - Biology of Melancholia (Box 1)
    Montassut's undated writings and notes on the biology of melancholia.
  - "Formes mineures de la mélancolie périodique", undated (Box 1)
  - History and criticisms of Melancholia, undated (Box 1)
    Montassut's undated writings and notes on the history and criticisms of melancholia research.
  - "Investigations psychiatriques en urologie", 1951 (Box 2)
  - "La dépression constitutionnelle", 1931-1965 (Box 2)
    Includes three publications under same title: 1931, 1935, 1965.
  - "La dépression constitutionnelle," revisions, undated (Box 2)
    Revised original manuscript by Montassut.
  - Lecture notes, 1928-1936 (Box 2)
    Files include lectures given and attended by Montassut.
  - "Les manics chroniques", undated (Box 2)
  - Psychogenesis of Melancholia (Box 2)
    Montassut's undated writings and notes on the psychogenesis of melancholia.
  - "Traitement du delirium tremens et des états mélancoliques", undated (Box 2)
  - "Valeur practique de la médecine psychosomatique", undated (Box 2)
    Published with L. Chertok.
- Subject Files
  Includes Montassut's notes on various topics in the field of psychiatry, as well as his comments on scholarly publications by other well-known psychiatrists.
  - Associated psychoses, undated (Box 2)
  - Ethiologie et Pathogenie, undated (Box 2)
  - "Étude sur l'hibernation", 1938 (Box 2)
  - "Hommage à J. H. Schultz", 1959 (Box 2)
  - "La neuro-psychiatrie dans le cadre de la réforme hospitalière et hospitalo-universitaire", undated (Box 2)
  - "Syndrôme de Cotard", 1920 (Box 2)